Guide to the Utility Workers Union of America, Local 1-2 Photographs PHOTOS.118
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Utility Workers Union of America, Local 1-2 Photographs
1940-1996
1980-1996
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Utility Workers Union of America. Local 1-2
PHOTOS.118
8.5 Linear Feet in 13 manuscript boxes and 2 record cartons.
5 videocassettes
Local 1-2 of the Utility Workers Union of America evolved out of the Utility Workers Organizing Committee (UWOC) established by the Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO) in 1938. In 1946, with more than 180 locals organized nationwide, the UWOC transformed itself into the Utility Workers Union of America, CIO. This collection includes photographs of meetings, events and rallies; individual and group portraits; 5 photo albums; VHS tapes; buttons, badges and hats; and personal artifacts from John McMahon, Secretary-Treasurer of Local 1-2. The the photographs and artifacts span from 1940 to 1996.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by the Utility Workers Union of America, Local 1-2 sent a gift of 6 boxes of photographs 1997 and 1998; additional materials were donated in 2003. The accession number associated with these gifts are 1997.064, NPA.2002.053, and NPA.2003.112.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into two series:
Series I: Events and Portraits; Series II: Photos Albums and Artifacts
Historical Note
The history of Local 1-2 properly begins with the Utility Workers Organizing Committee (UWOC) established by the Congress of Industrial Organizations in 1938. Previous practice within the industry had been to have company unions, easily controlled by management. Organizing was facilitated in the New York area by a merger of older local companies (New York Edison, Bronx Gas, the New Amsterdam Company, Central Union Gas, Northern Gas and others) into the Consolidated Edison Company(ConEd). One year after the merger the AFL-affiliated International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers (IBEW) obtained the right to represent ConEd employees, and soon issued charters to each of the seven company unions.
In 1940, after a bitter intra-union dispute in the IBEW between the newly organized utility workers and electrical workers, the ConEd employees pulled out of the international union. The seven utility locals constituted themselves as the Brotherhood of Consolidated Edison Employees. As a newly independent utility workers union, the body took the name Local 1-2, representing the separate identities of two major categories, plant and clerical employees, within ConEd. The governing Council of the Brotherhood included representatives of both categories of workers. The Brotherhood eventually came to represent all unionized workers at ConEd.
In 1945 the Brotherhood was invited to become part of the CIO's Utility Workers Organizing Committee; it would make a significant contribution to the size and power of this body. In 1946, with more than 180 locals organized nationwide, the UWOC transformed itself into the Utility Workers Union of America, CIO. Three of the top officers of the new international union came from New York's Local 1-2.
The first administration of Local 1-2 remained in office for seventeen years, with Paddy McGrath and Andrew McMann as president and Business Agent, and Richland and Marsini as Assistant Business Agents. The personal popularity of McGrath, combined with a system of elections which heavily favored the incumbents, assured the continuation in office of the old guard. In the mid-1950s challenges to the incumbents were mounted by a number of groups, including the United Social Club (Joe Murray), the Security Party (Jim Geoghegan), the Rider Avenue Committee (Sampson and McMann, who had split from the McGrath slate) and "Steam." At the same time, the insurgents attempted to change the by-laws, to replace the practice of system-wide elections and appointed business agents with section-based elections for Board members and business agents - and slates for top officers. In 1958, in a marathon caucus meeting at the New Yorker Hotel, the challengers finally got together and fielded a joint slate known as "The Coalition." In one of the first elections to be conducted by the American Arbitration Association; 16,000 out of 20,000 eligible voters participated. The ballots took several days to count and the opposition won by a substantial margin.
Despite a number of disputes and defections within the Coalition alliance, the new administration managed to remain in office until 1990, when a new insurgent group, the Justice Party turned them out after a hard-fought campaign. Against a backdrop of ongoing internal struggles, the Local also faced a number a challenges from the outside, and an uphill fight against ConEd's attempts to hold back wage increases, trim benefits, and shrink the workforce. Between 1958 and 1962 ConEd bought three power plants from the Transit Authority. Workers in these plants had been represented by Transport Workers Union, Local 101, and the transfer of the plants led to a battle between the TWU and Local 1-2 for jurisdiction over those workers. Local 1-2 emerged victorious, and thereby gained 2,000 members.
The Local has long faced serious health and safety issues, including high rates of cancer among members exposed to asbestos, PCB's, and other toxic substances, and severe injuries due to fire and explosions. There have also been debates within the union about discriminatory practices in ConEd hiring, about the use of nuclear power, and the constant threat of downsizing in the ConEd workforce. In 1968 the Local mounted a two-week strike, which resulted in a return to work with acceptance of the company's original offer. A more debilitating nine-week strike in 1983 resulted in losses for the union, and widespread dissatisfaction with the Local leadership among members. The company had responded quickly and effectively to the black-out threat, demonstrated its ability to run the system using supervisors and even handled a fire emergency in mid-town in record time. After the 1983 strike, the workforce, which had already declined from its 1958 peak of 25,000, was reduced through attrition to 13,000.
Hard times in the Local brought a new series of challenges to the leadership in the late 1980s. In the face of a serious threat from the Unity Party, headed by Mike Cotter, James Joy returned to the post of Business Manager of the Local after serving as International president. He arranged a temporary truce, creating a special post for Cotter - but strife continued, as the leadership sought to oust Cotter and a court-ordered election was held, which restored him to his post. A new round of by-laws changes resulted in the victory of the Justice Party, and its presidential candidate, John Goodman, in September 1990.
Sources:
For a more detailed history of the Local see the typescript survey report (Harry Van Arsdale Labor Records Project, Survey #387) produced by Jane Latour for the Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives in 1991.
Related Archival Materials
WAG 131 Guide to the Utility Workers Union of America, Local 1-2 Records
See also: Records of the Transport Workers Union of America (including TWU Local 101). The Record, the newspaper of Local 1-2.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of black and white and color photographs dating from 1940 until 1996, though the majority are from 1980 through the mid-1990s.
Series I: Events and Portraits (1940-1996) The images document Local 1-2 meetings, conferences, elections and negotiations, as well as rallies and pickets. Social events such as picnics, dinners and parties are also represented. The contentious election history of the Local, including the 1990 victory of the Justice Party, is evident in many photographs. There are a large number of group and individual portraits of Local 1-2 leadership.
Series II: Photo Albums and Artifacts (1940-1996) This series includes 5 photo albums documenting conferences and initiatives. Additionally, there are approximately 40 political and Local 1-2 buttons and ribbons, VHS tapes, hats, badges, and personal artifacts from Secretary-Treasurer John McMahon, such as collected business cards, eye glasses and religious items.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Labor unions -- Officials and employees.; Labor unions -- Organizing -- United States.; Strikes and lockouts -- Public utilities -- New York (State) -- New York.; New York (N.Y.).; Photographs.; Membership cards.; Buttons (information artifacts).; Identity cards.; Labor unions -- Elections -- New York (State) -- New York.; Electric industry workers -- Labor unions.; Collective labor agreements -- Public utilities.; Arbitration, Industrial.; Utility Workers Organizing Committee; International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers; Consolidated Edison Company of New York, inc.; Congress of Industrial Organizations (U.S.); American Federation of Labor
- Series I: Events and Portraits, 1940-1996
  - 1940 & 1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Dances, 1950s (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Picnics, 1950s (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1950s (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 50s-60s, 1950s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Local 1-2 Photographs, early 1960s (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1960s (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1970s (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1980s (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Local 1-2 Photographs, early 1970s (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1970s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 1980s (I) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1980s (II) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Colombians, 1985-1989 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - St Patrick's Parade, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Joy Reurns; Membership Meeting, Apr 1986 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Union Meeting, Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Whitfield, Charles: Retirement Dinner, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Union Meetings, 1987-1990 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Labor Day Parade, Aug 1988 - Sep 1988 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Membership Meeting, Sep 1988 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Picnic (Suntan Lake, NJ), Sep 1988 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Toys for Tots, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Utility Workers Local 1-2, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Breakfast for Graduates of Van Arsdale Labor School (Astoria Manor), 1989 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Solidarity Day, Jan 25, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Democratic Fundraiser, Feb 1989 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Membership Meeting, Feb 1989 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - 1989 (I) (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - 1989 (II) (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - 1989 (III) (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - 1990s (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - St Patrick's Day, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Rally at Irving Place (I), Mar 1989 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Rally at Irving Place (II), Jun 8, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Union Meeting (I), Jun 13, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Union Meeting (II), Jun 13, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Workers Memorial Day, Apr 28, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Swearing in of Officers, Jun 1989 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Rally (Westchester) (I), Jun 5, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Rally (Westchester) (II), Jun 5, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Company Sign, Irving Place, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Rally (Bronx), Jun 6, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - [Rally], Queens Boulevard, Jun 7 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Rally, Irving Place, Jun 8, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Link Up (I), Jun 13, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Link Up Pictures (Met Life, Con Ed, NY Life Rally), Jun 13, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Link Up (II), [Jun 13], 1989 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Link Up (III), [Jun 13], 1989 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Link Up Contract Negotiations (Human chain around Irving Place), 1989 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Columbian Party, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Gramercy Park, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Gramercy Park Funeral, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Membership Meeting, Sep 27, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Membership Meeting, Nov 21, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Gene [Briody], Cuomo and Walensa, Nov 1989 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Union Meeting, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Hellgate Explosions, Dec 24, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Health and Safety Committee, 1989-1990 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Labor Day Parade, 1989 or 1990 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - 1990 (I) (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - 1990 (II) (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - 1990s (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Safety Meeting about State Funding, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - James (Jimmy) Joy (I), Undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - James (Jimmy) Joy (II), Undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Key Players, 1945-1995 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Briody Administration (Meetings and Conferences), 1987-1990 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Memorial Service (Bruckner Blvd), Feb 1990 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Membership Meeting, Feb 1990 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Anniversary, 50th, 1995 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Anniversary, 50th: Dinner, 1995 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - President of Union, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - 3rd Cubicle Portraits (Kelly, Houlihan, Armstrong, Keenan, Sanchez), Undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Executive Board, Undated (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Group Pictures of Officers, 1986-1990 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Picnic, NJ, Undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - [1989] (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Officers, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Sanchez, Tony and Richard Besthoff, Undated (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - 2nd Cubicle Potraits (Cotter, Sommer, Gallione, Bencivenao, Lendino), Undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - COPE-Brooklyn, Undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Briody, Gene (I), 1987-1990 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Briody, Gene (II), Undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Gene Radio Show, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Memorial Service (American Legion Post 1124), Undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Officers, Local and National, Undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Election Board, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - 1st Cubicle Portraits (Zummo, Mastro, Papa, Providence, Clancy), Undated (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Ryan, Willie (National Representative from Local 1-2), Undated (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Westerkamo (President of the Mutual Aid Society), Undated (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Cuomo, Mario, Undated (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - National Officers (Mike Kenny and Marshall Hicks), Undated (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Eastern Rally, Mar 4 1989 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Local 1-2, Aug 1, 1991 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Utility Workers, Undated (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Retirement Party, Undated (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Elections, Undated (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Elections (II), Undated (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - General Membership Meeting, Feb 10, 1993 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Unidentified Meeting, Undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Elections (III), Undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Portraits, Undated (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Membership Meeting, Undated (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Rally, Apr 23, 1996 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Photos from the Files of John McMahon, Undated (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Group Portraits, Undated (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Regional Conference; Various Events, Oct 5, 1992-Oct 7, 1992; Undated (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Events and Portraits, 1993-1994 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Various Events (I), Undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Group Portraits, Undated (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Various Events (II), Undated (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Various Events (III), Undated (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Various Events (IV), Undated (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Meetings, Undated (Box 12, Folder 6)
- Series II: Photo Albums and Artifacts, 1945-1996
  - Album: "Pictures", undated (Box 13)
  - Album: "The Record" (Con Edison Post 1174 Hospital Visitation Committee), 1944-1975 (Box 13)
  - Album: Conference (Washington, D.C.) (I), 1989 (Box 13)
  - Album: Conference (Washington, D.C.) (II), 1989 (Box 13)
  - Album: Constitutional Convention, 23rd (Hollywood, Florida), Jun 24, 1987 - Jun 27, 1987 (Box 14)
  - Badges, undated (Box 15)
  - Buttons, undated (Box 14)
  - Hats, undated (Box 15)
  - McMahon, John: Personal Artifacts, undated (Box 14)
  - Stickers, undated (Box 15)
  - VHS Tapes, 1994, undated; 5 videocassettes (Box 15)